Miguel Ruiz

New Graduate and Former Park Ranger

Totowa, NJ 07512 miguelruiz5100@gmail.com +1 973 905 1131

After working for more than five years for the federal government and learning valuable skills from the National Park Service, I am ready to transfer my skills to gain more experience in the private sector. I hope to prove how my skills as a well-trained park ranger can transfer to any workplace that values clients and customers. I also recently graduated Summa Cum Laude at Rutgers University with my Bachelor's degree in public affairs and administration. I am ambitious and seeking a challenge that can combine my public sector experience with my specialized academic skills in the field!

Authorized to work in the US for any employer

Work Experience

Administrative Assistant

U.S. National Park Service - Paterson, NJ December 2022 to Present

Administrative services that supports the mission of the National Park Service, which include all business and human resource elements towards the park that I was assigned to.

AmeriCorps Member

AmeriCorps - Paterson, NJ September 2022 to Present

Tutoring 9-12 grade students in activities and homework help

Program Coordinator

New Jersey Community Development Corporation - Paterson, NJ July 2022 to Present

- Acted as professional liaison to the National Park Service (NPS) and the non-profit partner organization, New Jersey Community Development Corporation (NJCDC).
- Led a collaborative joint program between the NPS and NJCDC called the Great Falls Youth Corps (GFYC), a team of summer interns offering visitor services to the public of the Paterson Great Falls National Historical Park.
- Managed intern onboarding processes, including paperwork such as W-9s, media release forms, etc.
- Managed training sessions, both formal and on-site, for the interns.
- Acted as direct supervisor to the interns.
- Mentored interns in other job aspects such as interpretation, safety culture, and knowledge of the park's history.
- Managed payroll for interns and acted as timekeeper for their work schedule.
- Coordinated with NPS rangers and administrative staff to utilize the interns in park events and daily programming such as serving at the orientation table or beautification tasks (picking up trash, cleaning the park...)

- Coordinated with NJCDC and NPS administration to organize field trips for the interns to other national park sites.
- Created and maintained event and field trip itineraries for interns and park staff.

Grant Writer / Program Assistant (Intern)

New Jersey Community Development Corporation - Paterson, NJ January 2021 to December 2021

- Assisted in grant writing applications and achieved in competing against major nonprofits to receive over \$100,000 in grant funding for the recreational program (NBC Grant)
- Formulated over 400 program applications for a grant-funded program to provide food to families impacted by COVID-19.
- Interviewed and spoke with families about their needs and assessed them with training and supervision.
- Integrated paper applications for the food program onto a database that provided convenience and accountability for supervisors
- · Received a stipend gifted from the organization for my service and dedicated work

Seasonal Park Ranger

U.S. National Park Service - Paterson, NJ May 2019 to December 2021

- Employed as a federal interpretive park ranger that worked as an official park tour guide and interpreter of the history, culture, and resources.
- Park Guides focus on more responsibilities such as programs and larger projects that affect the public either daily or for a specific timeframe (event days).
- Managed a team of interns as a lead supervisor and hiring officer.
- Served as a liaison between cooperating nonprofit and the National Park Service.
- Provided over 200+ tours that consist of 45 minutes to an hour.
- Answered phone calls and coordinated with visitors virtually to provide information and assistance.
- Able to walk/stand for prolonged periods of time.
- Talked to over 10,000 visitors during my seasons.
- Received monetary and official awards for my public service (STAR)
- Organized events such as public cleanups and large-scale tours of over 100 visitors per tour.
- · Assisted and directed tours and talks for visitors of all ages including young children.

Student Computer Lab Assistant

Passaic County Community College - Paterson, NJ January 2019 to March 2020

- Opening/Closing the library at Passaic County Community College, Paterson Campus.
- Maintaining computer lab area with 10-50 students who might need assistance.
- In charge of all computer applications including printers and all computers that students use.
- Trained in safety and emergency procedure in case of fire, hazard, or lethal threat.
- Responsible for checking the lab and enforcing the rules of the library.
- Assisted in answering questions regarding the college or library to students.
- Assisted in computer help to students having any problem.
- Assisted problems consisted of but not limited to: helping students log into computers, adjusting their format on documents, printing documents, how to email professors, etc...)
- Checking for any technical problems that can be resolved within my power. (Paper jamming, network issues, log-in issues.)
- Routinely checked and replaced toner and paper in printers of the library.

Visitor Services Assistant

U.S. National Park Service - Paterson, NJ June 2018 to December 2018

- Employed as a federal interpretive park ranger that worked as an official park tour guide and interpreter of the history, culture, and resources under the National Park Service.
- Handled visitor services that entail giving them directions, answering any questions, and offering any information regarding the park.
- Operated a cash register and managed a bookstore.
- Kept inventory of the bookstore
- Followed opening procedures and counted money for the day.
- Followed closing procedures and counted money for the day and prepare for the following workday prior to leaving.
- Landscaped and operated trail and lawn equipment to restore and maintain park trails and areas.
- Created multiple programs for the public and for park special events.

Server/Cashier

The Fine Grind Coffee and Bar - Wayne, NJ December 2016 to June 2017

Responsibilities included but not limited to:

- -taking and traveling orders from barista and chef with each table (usually full house.)
- -Handle drinks and food and serve them to customers in an orderly and timely fashion.
- -Treat each customer with respect and quality customer service.
- -Cashier trained and took down orders through computer and paper transactions (credit, debit, gift card, cash, etc.)

Education

Master of Public Administration in Public Financial Management

Rutgers University - Newark, NJ September 2021 to Present

Bachelor of Arts in Public Affairs and Administration

Rutgers University - Newark, NJ September 2020 to May 2022

Associate in Arts (AA) in Humanities

Passaic County Community College - Paterson, NJ September 2018 to May 2020

High school or equivalent in Engineering

International High School/Garrett Morgan Academy - Paterson, NJ September 2014 to June 2018

Skills

- Microsoft Word (10+ years)
- Microsoft Excel (3 years)

- Microsoft PowerPoint (10+ years)
- Public Speaking (4 years)
- Training (2 years)
- Inventory (2 years)
- Organizational Skills (4 years)
- Leadership Development (4 years)
- Interpretation (8 years)
- Computer Networking
- · Team Management

Languages

- English Expert
- Spanish Intermediate

Groups

Paterson Youth Council

September 2014 to June 2016

Youth Ambassador and involve volunteer service and opportunities to gain civic knowledge

Great Falls Teen Center

September 2013 to June 2016

Member of organization for family skills, life skills, academic skills, and seek mentorship.

New Jersey Community Development Corporation

September 2013 to February 2021

Volunteer/Hired employee/Various member of different programs

Publications

Great Falls Youth Corps Visits Joshua Tree National Park

 $\frac{http://www.njcdc.org/\sim njcdc/news-events/!/index.php?Great-Falls-Youth-Corps-Visits-Joshua-Tree-National-Park-53}{National-Park-53}$

August 2015

Great Falls Teen Center Students Honored

http://www.njcdc.org/mobile/post.php?num=105 June 2016

Paterson youth group tackles water sampling project to address lead contamination

http://www.northjersey.com/story/news/paterson-press/2016/09/26/paterson-youth-group-tackles-water-sampling-project-to-address-lead-contamination/93024794/ September 2016

Paterson students stand in presidential shoes in mock debate

 $\frac{http://www.northjersey.com/story/news/paterson-press/2016/11/07/paterson-students-stand-in-presidential-shoes-in-mock-debate/93544050/$

November 2016

Additional Information

I am an outgoing individual that loves to do things outside of the box.

Some problems I face are problems I have never faced before and yet I still solve them efficiently. I am well-managed and organized. Ethical and respectful both in and out of the workplace. Very diligent in not only getting my work done but going out of my way to do more.